Guide to the Martha Gayle Collection BCMS.0050
Brooklyn Collection
Martha Gayle Collection
1902-2001
1960-1985
Brooklyn Collection
BCMS.0050
2.62 Linear Feet in 6 document boxes [5 Letter size, 1 legal]
Various documents relating to the life, work, and activities of Martha Adina Gayle dating from 1902 -2001. Gayle was a Jamaican immigrant who came to the United States in 1924.
Biographical Note
Martha Adina Gayle was born in the parish of St. Elizabeth in the district of Cambridge on the island of Jamaica on October 22, 1902. According to her birth records, she was the daughter of Olivia and Richard Gayle. On April 16 1924, Martha traveled to the United States of America on board the S.S. Alegria from Port Antonio, Jamaica, landing six days later on April 22nd with her final destination being Brooklyn, New York. Records listed Martha's occupation as a domestic worker and that she was not married.
Having established a good footing in the United States, Martha Gayle was able to accommodate and help her niece Daisy May Parnell, who lived with her in Brooklyn for many decades. Martha was also very helpful to her family in Jamaica with correspondence records indicating that she often helped out in whatever way she could. On April 15, 1947 Martha became a naturalized citizen of the United States of America. For the next few decades, Martha lived in the Bedford-Stuyvesant area of Brooklyn where she started out renting and eventually owned three apartment buildings at 164 MacDonough Street, 51 MacDonough Street and 285 Macon Street. It was through the rental income those properties provided that Martha was able to transition from domestic work to self-employment as a landlord.
Martha was a very active and longstanding member of the Siloam Presbyterian church as well as a women's missionary group. In the latter years of her life, Martha had several health issues and was in and out of the hospital. Records indicate that she had serious health issues in the year 2000 and at one point was living in a hospice. She passed away in 2000 at approximately 98 years old.
Scope and Contents
The materials in this collection are largely textual and contain records such as correspondence, medical documents, and identification papers. There are also records relating to Gayle's niece Daisy Parnell, as well as Arnold Austin, another relative. A large part of the collection consists of financial records that speak to her activities as a landlord such as banking, legal, insurance, and utilities records. The collection also includes photographs and ephemera.
The richest section of this collection is the extensive correspondence between Martha Gayle, Daisy Parnell, and their friends and family back home. While many of their correspondents' full names are unknown, their communications nonetheless provide an understanding of the relationship that Martha and Daisy both had with their families and friends. Correspondents include Martha's sister Edith Gayle, her onetime employer Addie Place, and many others.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to researchers without restriction.
Provenance
The Martha Gayle Collection was donated to the Brooklyn Collection in January 2016 by George Camarda, who purchased Martha Gayle's home after her death and found these materials stored in the basement.
Arrangement
The collection is comprised of six boxes of records that are arranged in eight series by type.
Related Materials
Brooklyn Clippings Files, folders: Bedford-Stuyvesant (1960-1989) and West Indian Americans
Forde, F. Donnie. Caribbean Americans in New York City. New York: Arcadia Publishing, 2002.
Kasinitz, Phillip. Caribbean New York: Black Immigrants and the Politics of Race. New York: Cornell University Press, 1992.
Bedford-Stuyvesant (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.)
- Series 1: Personal Documents
  - Identification Records, 1902-1947 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Medical Records, 1956-2001 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Personal Notes, 1955- (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Notebook/Ledger, 1987-1990 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Address Books, 1961- (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Arnold L. Austin Passport, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Note
    This item is in fragile condition.
- Series 2: Financial Documents
  - Bank Books, 1940-1995 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Car Repair Fines and Bills, 1963-1988 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Con Edison Bills, 1952-1982 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Con Edison Bills, 1983-2001 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Gas Bills, 1970-2001 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Legal Documents, 1946-1970 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Savino Heat and Oil Bills, 1979-1982 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Tax Documents, 1945-1993 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Telephone Bills, 1971 (Jan - March) (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Water Bills, 1971-2000 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Arnold Austin Tax Return, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Invoices, Bank Statements, and Receipts, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Invoices, Receipts and Bank Statements, 1945-1997 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Insurance Documents, 1948-1998 (Box 6, Folder 2)
- Series 3: Properties
  - 51 MacDonough Street, 1941-1990 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - 164 MacDonough Street, 1942-2001 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - 285 Macon Street, 1915-2001 (Box 6, Folder 5)
- Series 4: Correspondence
  Arrangement
  The folders in this series are arranged by the sender's name. In some cases, only the sender's first name is known.
  - Addie Place, 1947-1949 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    Addie Place was at one time Martha Gayle's employer and sold her the house at 164 MacDonough Street.
  - Aunt Ross, 1967-1969 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Austin, R., 1944-1945 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    Martha Gayle's sister.
  - Carmen, 1973-1991 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    Martha Gayle's niece.
  - Cliff to Arnold L. Austin, 1963-1972 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    Cliff is Martha Gayle's nephew.
  - Cliff to Daisy Parnell and Martha Gayle, 1961-1994 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Edna, 1978-1986 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Estella, 1988-1991 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Gayle, Edith, 1952-1975 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    Edith Gayle is Martha's sister, and Daisy Parnell's mother.
  - Gayle, Martha, 1963-1993 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Graham Family, 1993- (Box 2, Folder 19)
    The Graham Family correspondence comes from grandnieces and grandnephews of Martha Gayle.
  - June (includes photograph), 1979-1994 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Leslie, Inez and Linda, 1968-1998 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    Inez Leslie was Martha Gayle's niece and Linda Leslie was Inez's daughter.
  - Luc, 1948-1987 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Miller Family, 1972-1996 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    The Miller Family correspondence comes from grandnieces and grandnephews of Martha Gayle.
  - Parnell, Daisy, 1981 February-May (Box 3, Folder 4)
    Daisy Parnell is Martha Gayle's niece who lived with her for many years. She is also Edith Gayle's daughter.
  - Reynolds, Julius, 1978-1979 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Rowe, D., 1977-1979 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Ruby, 1969-1995 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Stokely, 1986-1988 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Sue, 1931-1976 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Sender Unknown (Box 3, Folder 10)
    Arranged by date.
  - Single Letters (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Undated Correspondence (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Greeting Cards (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Official Correspondence (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Envelopes (Box 6, Folder 6)
- Series 5: Photographs
  - Photographs of Martha Gayle (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Photographs of Daisy Parnell (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Individual Portraits (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Group portraits (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Children (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Series 6: Church Documents
  - Bibles & Birthday Card in Portfolio (Box 4)
  - Books and Pamphlets (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Leaflets and Letters (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Siloam Presbyterian Church (Box 6, Folder 8)
- Series 7: Ephemera
  - Calendars (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Sheet Music (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - New York World's Fair 1964/65 Guidebooks (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Programs and Books (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Booklets and Flyers (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Prints and Stamps (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Non-personal Photographs and Postcards (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Scrapbook Materials (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Funeral Programs, 1972-1992 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    Included is a program for Edith Gayle, Martha Gayle's sister and Daisy Parnell's mother, which has a family photograph tucked inside.
- Series 8: Daisy Parnell
  - Church Documents, 1949-1978 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1998 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Educational Documents, 1960-1971 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Financial Documents and Receipts, 1945-1988 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Identification Documents, 1945-1957 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Medical Documents, 1955-1980 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Official Correspondence, 1945-2001 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Tax Documents, 1949-2000 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Water Bills, 1975-1979 (Box 5, Folder 16)